<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The enquirie and verdite of the quest panneld of the death of Richard Hune wich was founde hanged in Lolars tower</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1537</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845438</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 53:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The enquirie and verdite of the quest panneld of the death of Richard Hune wich was founde hanged in Lolars tower</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>H. Peetersen van Middleburch?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Antwerp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1537?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>At end: Subscribed in this maner Thomas Barnewell Crawner of the citie of London.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-c⁴.</note>
                  <note>Destroyed; preserved on UMI microfilm reel 53.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hunne, Richard, d. 1514 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10337:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10337:1"/>
            <p>¶The enquirie and verdite of the queſt pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neld of the death of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Hune wich was founde hanged in Lolars tower.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10337:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10337:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſee (mooſt deare Reader) how ſuttellie the trueth is euer perſequuted might ſeame grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te woonder / but that the holie goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte hath oft tymes ſhewed and teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scripture that hit ſhuld ſo be. What kynd of perſequucion hath bene vnproued? what can be imagined that hathe not hitherto bene prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſede concerning ſoche thynges? In ſome places they heede &amp; afterward burne / in ſome places they bringe ſtraighte wayſe to the fyre. When that ſhift will not ſerue / or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dare not hurte the perſon liuyng by cauſe of his riches or power &amp;c. yet wyll they burne him after he died peaſablie in his bed / as they dide Wicleffe &amp; Tracie with other / to kepe the ſymple innocent ſowles wich they haue made blyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſtill to continewe in darknes / ſayyng / he was an heretique who ſo euer kepe his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhalbe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned lyuyng / and ſo the burning of that which feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te no paine is a greate feare to the ignoraunt that ſeith hit.</p>
            <p>Some be cauſe they be wyſe and vtter the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſye and abhominable lyuing of whorehunters with diſcrete communicacion / ſo that no man can gayne ſaye or accuſe them but they ſay trweth be brought in to preſone and hereſies fained oute of hande that be ſparppled abrode to the people with all the apparence of veritie that can be diuiſed to perſuade them that the parties be not preſoned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued / wich if they wyll not confeſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to be openlie abiured to theyre greate ſhame
<pb facs="tcp:10337:3"/> theire neckes be broken or elles they be ſome other wiſe conueyde / and after hanged vp / and than ſaide and preached to that they hanged them ſealues / as was this Hune / wich to be trewe thou ſhal eaſelie perceaue by the enquirie and verdite of the queeſt here in this litell treatiſe conteyned. yf they be poo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and want frendes and no euident cauſe founde wherfore they ſhuld ſuffre / then die they in preſone no man knowith howe / hit is ſtraight waiſe ſaide if any man axe of them that they died of one diſeaſe or other and no mooe woordes ar made. yf a man knowyng theyre malicyouſe hertes get hym fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from daunger in to ſome other realme / wich haplie is to circumſpect to be taken by any commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne officer or knowen enemie / ſtraighte waye cauſe they one or other for money to play Iudas part and to make him ſealf greate with the partie / &amp; as thow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe he fauored him ſingularlie to make moche on hym tyll he ſee his tyme &amp; than betray him / as they haue euen now played with William Tyndal a man of ſynguler vertuouſnes and of no leſſe lernyng and iugement in ſcripture and of a rare gentillnes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicions as all they can teſtyfie that knewe him and vſed familiaritie with him. Summa to kepe vp the Kyngdome of fornicatours and aduowtrers that they may liue in all pleaſure and ydelnes / ſeruyng theyre belies onelie and lyuing more viciouſlie than euer did the hethen / &amp; for the enſtabliſhement ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to thruſt downe vertuouſe lyuyng and trew prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chyng hath no ſotteltie bene vnſought for / nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſhalbe I feare me of theyre parties / vntyll they be yet brought lower / I ſpeake of the bad / for the good as they haue in euerie place for the mooſt part
<pb facs="tcp:10337:3"/> to litell ſo can they not haue to moche. Thus ſeiſt thou theire practiſe before this tyme vſed how they haue with all ſottelltie perſequuted them that of good zeale and loue haue frelie ſpoken the trueth / and how they haue hyd and clocked that they dyd with the apparence of holines / as thowghe they had done hit to extinct hereſies / for ſo made they the people to beleue. Other frutes haue they hither to not brought forth. So long ſpace violentlie to haue ſubdued goddes holie woord weere as me ſemyth to moche and the tyme now counuenient with haſt to reforme them ſealues and to prepare theire hartes louynglye to receaue the woorde of theire ſowles health and wyllynglie to diſtribute hit to the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ignoraunte people / euerye man accordyng to his gift / yet ſe I not that they be any thing wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng therunto but rather in mynde to rage moare then they did before.</p>
            <p>The light is now broken forth (thankes be to the Lorde) mager theire beardes / and they brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght in no ſmall feare of ſodaine ruine of theire kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gdome / yet by cauſe they ſe the world hath not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forſaken theire deceyuable doctrine in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / they hope of a chaunge / and haue theire ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te conſpiriſies deuiſed with all ſutteltie to bryng that to pas / the good they do they do by compulſion and for feare of loſyng theire poſſeſſions / hitherto is there no ſygne of repentaunce taken in herte for theire abhominacions ſo long vſed. Styll lyue they as they did before / they ar no les deſirouſe of promo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion / no les delited in bely Ioye / in wealfaring / in gorgiouſe rayment / as readie to abhorre chaſt matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monye and daylie to commit whordome and aduou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie
<pb facs="tcp:10337:4"/>
/ as lothe to do the buſines wich they ar onelie bound to as euer they weere / I meane to preache with ſynceritie goddes wholie woorde and that for loue and zeale that they haue to ſe chriſten lyuing floriſſhe and not for the fylthie lukres ſake. They ſtand but at a ſtay tyll they may fynd by one mean is or other awaye to bryng in theyre olde accoſtomed vices to be counted holines / as they in tymes paſt haue made the world to beleue. They do but diſſeam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble in vtwarde apperaunce / in hert they be infect w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyre accoſtomed traterie / euer readie when occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhalbe geuen to playe theyre partes a thowſand tymes moare tyranniouſlie than euer they did. So leaue they theire olde furiouſe heyte of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kquelling that neuertheleſſe they ſtyll intend yet ones a gayne to raiſe hit vp. what hertes haue theſe men? what token of meaknes and ſofferaunce is yet eſpied in them: what ſigne of retorne from theire vnſpekable malice? wich ſpringeth of no nother thyng than of auarice &amp; deſire to liue voluptuouſlie. Thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be good note I not but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euyll nether hate I or wold any man ſhuld hate the perſons of them but the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / wich I wold gladlie were amended not increa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. If we touch them neuer ſo littell then heare we that we rayle on them / blaſpheme them / belie them and ſpeake vncharitablie by them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to wich thyng I thus anſwere / yf they wold indifferentlie ſerch what is ſaide &amp; applie hit to the reule of haritie they ſhuld fynd no thyng ſpoken but trueth / no thyng ſo ſharpelie touched as is of theyre parte deſerued. Leat euerie man wich fyndeth hym ſealf anie thing greued deſcend in to iugment of his awne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and axe what hit ſaith / wich yf they wold often
<pb facs="tcp:10337:4"/> do they ſhuld ſone fynde all that is ſpoken to be les than the trueth / ſeme hit at the fyrſt neuer ſo ſharp or rigouroſe. Nether is euerie ſharp woord vnchari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table / except S. Iohn baptiſt were not wel auiſed when he called the Pharizees &amp; Saducees the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracion of vipers Mat. iij. or oure ſauioure Chriſt oute of charitie vſyng the ſealf woordes. Math. xij. And agayne ſayyng to them woo be to you Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes pharizees hipocrites. Mat. xxiij. Luce. xi. &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viij. of Iohn calleth he them the ſonnes of the deuill. Sainct Paule alſo to one Elimas a ſocerer was not a ferde to ſaye. O full of ſotteltie and deceytful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the chyld of the deuill and the enemy of al right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſnes thou ceaſiſt not to peruert the ſtraightwai ſe of the lord. Acto. xiij. Men may not liue as blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de as betelles / as ignoraunt as aſſes / as ſottell as foxis / as lecherouſe as gootes / moare beaſtlie than beaſtes / and loke ſtyll that God wyll ſuffer them ether to be vnſpoken of or vnpunnyſſhed / but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhuld think that theire offences be (as the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is) ſo hanouſe that no tong can expreſſe them no hand endite them no wit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend them &amp; ſorow and repent them and continuallie praye to theyre moſt mercifull father to geue them ſome ſparkell of grace wherbie the may amende them.</p>
            <p>Leat falſhed giue place to the trueth. Leat viciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe lyuing be hated / and vertue had in price. Leat rancor be torned in to loue vnfayned. Leat the ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beare with the ignoraunt ſo far as may be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered / and the ignoraunt be obſequiouſe to heare the lerned: ye leat the lerned rather ſtudie one to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable to a nother / and one charitablie and indifferentlie heare a nother / and diſpute with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:10337:5"/> not with braunlyng and a gree louinglie with oute ſcholdyng / euery man knowyng that he may erre &amp; excludyng ſealff wyll and ſiniſtre iugement and than no doute but all ſharp monicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhall ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and in theire ſteade ſuccede praiſe to the eternall God / in whoſe power hit onelye lyeth this thyng to performe and a mongeſt men greate loue and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corde / and alſo thankes geuyng for his ineſtimab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le goodnes / to whom be all honoure and praiſe for euer. Amen.</p>
            <p>Of theire dyuers and manyfold facions this be ſufficient at this tyme / now her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the enquirie and ſentens geuen concernyng the death of the affor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaide Richard Hune.</p>
            <p>Reade Reader and iuge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10337:5"/>
            <p>THe .v. and the .vj. daye of Dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber / in the .vi. yere of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reygne of oure ſuffrayne Lord King Henry the .viij. Wylli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Barnwel / Crowner of London / the daye &amp; ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re aboue ſaide / with in the warde of Caſtilbayner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of London Aſſembled in a queſt whoſe names afterward do appere / and hath ſworne them treuly to enquere of the death of one Richard hune / which latelie was fownde deed in the lolars towre / with in paules church of London wheruppon all we of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inqueſte to geather went vp in to the ſaide towre / where we fownd the bodie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide hune hangyng vpon a ſtaple of Iron / in a gyrdel of ſylcke / with fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re countinaunce / his heed fayre kemmyd / &amp; his bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net right ſyttyng a pon his heed / with his eyne and mouth fayre cloſed / with oute any ſtaryng / gapyng / or frowning. Alſo with oute any dreueling or ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng in any place of his bodye. Where vpon by one aſſent all we agreede / to take downe the bodie of the ſaide hune / and as ſone as we began to heue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodie hit was looſe / wherbie by good aduiſement we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued that the gyrdel had no knot a boue the ſcaple / but hit was double caſt / and lynckes of an Iron chay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne which dyd hang on the ſame ſtaple were leyde a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame gyrdell wherby he did hang. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knot of the gyrdel that went aboute his neck ſtoode vnder his lefte eare / wich cauſed his heed to leyne toward his right ſhoulder. Natwithſtandyng there came ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of his noſe turles .ij. ſmall ſtreames of blode to the quantitie of .iiij. droppes Saue onelie theſe .iiij. drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of blode / the face / lippes / chynne / doublet / collar &amp; ſhurte of the ſaide Hune was cleane from any blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de Alſo we fynde that the ſkyn bothe of his necke / &amp; throte by nethe the gyrdel of ſylcke / was freat &amp; faſed
<pb facs="tcp:10337:6"/> awaye / with that thyng which the murtherars had bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken his necke withall. Alſo the handes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide Hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne were wrong in the wryſtes: werby we perceyued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his handes hade bene bounde.</p>
            <p>More ouer we fynde that with in the ſaide priſonne was no meane wherby any man myght hang hym ſeal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe but onelie a ſtole / wich ſtole ſtode a pon a bolſter of a bed / ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yckel that any man or beeſt might not tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hit ſo litell but hit was readie to fall. Wherby we perceyued that hit was not poſſible that Hune myght hang hym ſealfe the ſtole ſo ſtandyng. Alſo all the gyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dell from the ſtaple to his necke / as well as the part wich we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aboute his necke was to lytel for his heed to cum oute there at. Alſo hit was not poſſible that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſoft ſilken gyrdel ſhuld breake his neck or ſkynne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyrdel. Alſo we fynde in a corner / ſome what be younde the place where he did hang a greate percel of bloude. Alſo we fynde that apon the leafte ſyde of hunnes Iacket from the breaſte dounwarde be greate ſtreames of bloude. Alſo with in the flappe of the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te ſyde of his Iacket / we fynde a greate clouſter of bloude / and the Iacket foolden downe theruppon / wich thyng the ſaide Hun coude neuer foold nor doo after he was hanged. Wherbie hit aperitith playnlie to vs all that the neck of hune was broken / and the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te plentie of bloude was ſhede before he was hanged. Wherfore all we fynd by God &amp; all oure conſciences / that Richard hune was murthered / alſo we aquite the ſaide richard hune of his awne deeth</p>
            <p>Alſo an ende of a wax candel wich as Iohn Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynger ſaith he left in the preſone burnyng with hune that ſame ſondaie at night that Hune was murdered wich wax candel we founde ſtickyng apon the ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes faire put oute / aboute vij. or viij. fote from the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce where hune was hangede / wich candel after oure
<pb facs="tcp:10337:6"/> opinion was neuer put oute by him / for many likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoodes wich we haue perceyued. Alſo at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goyng vp of maſter Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celer in to lolars tower we haue good profe that there laye on the ſtockkes a gowne ether of murrey or crymſon in grayne furred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes / who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe gowne hit was we coulde neuer proue / nether who bare hit waye. All we fynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> M. William horſey chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celer to my lorde of londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath had at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule &amp; gyding of the ſaide priſonner / by all the tyme of his impreſonement. Moreouer all we fynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide maſter Horſey Chaunceler hath put oute charles Ioſeph of his office / as the ſaide charlis hath confeſſed by cauſe he wold not deale and vſe the ſaide priſonner ſo cruelly / and do to hym as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celer wolde haue had him to do. Notwithſtonding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keyys deliueraunce to the Chaunceler by charlis on the ſatyrday at night before hunnes deeth / <note place="margin">ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ey man to blyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel</note> and charles ryding oute of the towne on the ſondaye in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng enſuyng was but a conuencion made be twyxt Charlis and the Chaunceler / for to coloure the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / for the ſame ſondaye that Charles rode forthe he cam agayne to towne the ſame ſondaye nyght and kylled richard hune / as in the depoſicions of Iulian Lyttel / Thomas Chytcheley / Thomas Symondes / and Peter Torner dothe appere</p>
            <p>After colouring of the murther be twyxt charles and the Chaunceler conſpired / the Chaunceler called to him one Iohn ſpaldyng bellrynger of Paules / &amp; deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame bellrynger y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keyys of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lowlars tower geuyng to the ſaide belrynger a greate charge / ſaing I charge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to kepe Hun more ſtraytelie than he hath bene kept / and let him haue but one meale a daye. Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reouer I charge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leat no bodie come to him without my licence / nether bryng ſhurte / kappe / kercheffe / or any other thyng / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſee hit before hit come to him
<pb facs="tcp:10337:7"/> Alſo before Hune was caried to fulham the Chaunce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to be put apon hunnys necke a greate coller of Iron with a greate chayne wich is to heuy for any beeſt to were and long to endure.</p>
            <p>More ouer hit is well proued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before Hunnes deeth the ſaide Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celer cam vp in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide lolars tower &amp; knelyd downe before Hun / holdyng vp his handes to him / prayyng hym of forgyuenes of all that he hath do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to hym and muſt do to hym. And on the ſondaye fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowing the Chaunceler commaunded the penete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſarie of Paules / to go vp to him and ſaye him a Goſpel / &amp; make for him holie bred and holie water / and geue hit to him which ſo did / and after the Chaunceler com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that hune ſhuld haue his dynner / And the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me dynner tyme Charlis boye was ſhut in preſonne with Hun / wiche was neuer ſo before / and after dyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner when the belrynger fet oute the boye / the belryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſaide to the ſame boye / come no moare hither with meate for him vntyll to morow at noone / for maſter Chaunceler hath commaunded that he ſhall haue but one meale daye and the ſame nyght folowing Richard hune was murthered / wich murther conde not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve bene done with oute conſent and licens of the Chaunceler / and alſo by the wyttyng and knowlege of Iohn ſpaldyng belrynger / for there conde no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come in to the preſone but by the keyys / beyng in Iohn bellryngers keapyng.<note place="margin">No he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he ſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d neu ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e moare for he ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>d prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his dynner agaynſt the mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aye</note> Alſo as by my Lorde of Londons booke dothe appere Iohn bellrynger is a poore innocent man / wherfore all we do perce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue that this murther conde not be done but by the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Chaunceler / and by the wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng and knowyng of Iohn belrynger</p>
            <p>Charles Ioſeph with in the tower of London / of his awne frewyl and vnconſtreyned ſaide / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chaunceler deuiſed / and wrote wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h his awne
<pb facs="tcp:10337:7"/> hande / all ſuche heriſies as were layde to hunnes charge Reacord / Iohn god / Iohn truye / Iohn paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mar / Richard Gybſon with manie other</p>
            <p>Alſo charles Ioſeph ſaith that whan Richard hune was ſlayne / Iohn belrynger bare vp the ſtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in to the lolars tower awar candell / hauyng the keyys of the dores ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyng on his arme / and I char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les went next to him / and maſter Chaunceler cam vp laſt / and when all we cam vp / we founde hune ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng on his bed / and then maſter Chaunceler ſaide laye handes on the theffe / and ſo al we iij. murthered hune / and then I charles put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyrdell aboute Hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes neck / and then Iohn bellrynger and I Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les did heue vp Hune and maſter Chaunceler pulled the gyrdel ouer the ſtaple and ſo Hune was hanged</p>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>¶The depoſicion of Iulian lyttel late ſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to Charles Ioſeph / by hyr frewyl on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned the xiiij. day of Februarie / in the vi. yere of oure ſoueraine lorde Kyng Henrie the viij within the chappel of oure ladie of Bedlem ſhewyd to thynqueſt</head>
               <p>Fyrſt Iulian ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wenneſdaye of night after the deeth of Richard hune that Charles Ioſeph her maſter cam home in to his houſe at x. of the clocke in the nyght / and ſet hym downe to his ſupper / then Iulian ſaide to hym / ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter hit was tolde me that ye were in preſone / Char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les anſwered / hit is mearie to turne the penie / and after ſpuper / Charles truſſed percell of his goodes / &amp; with help of Iulian bare them in to maſtres por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars houſe to kepe / and that done Charles ſaide to Iulian. Iulian if thou wilt be ſworne to kepe my councel / I will ſhew the my mynde Iulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwered ye / yf hit be nether felonie nor treaſon / then Charles
<pb facs="tcp:10337:8"/> toke a boke oute of his purſſe / and Iulian ſware to hym theruppon / then ſaide Charles to Iulian. I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue diſtroyed Richard Hune. Alas maſter ſaide Iulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how / he was called a honeſt man / Charles anſwered I put a wyre in hys noſe / Alas ſaide Iulian now be yow caſt awaye &amp; vndone / than ſaide Charles / Iuli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an I truſt in the that thou wilt keape my councell / &amp; Iulian anſwered ye / but for gooddes ſake maſter ſhyft for youre ſealffe / &amp; than Charles ſaide / I had leuer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a C. lib. it were not doone / but that is doone can not be vndone / Moreouer Charles ſaide than to Iulian / vppon ſondaye when I rode to my coſynne to baryngtons houſe / I taried there and made good chere all daye tyll hit was night / and yet before hit was mydnyght I was in London / and had kylled Hune / &amp; apon the next daye I rode thither agayne and was there at dynner / and ſent for neyghburs &amp; made good chere / than Iulian axed Charles / where ſet yowe youre horſſe that night ye cam to towne / &amp; wherfore cam you not whome / Charles anſwered / I cam not whome for feare of bewrayyng / and than Iulian axed Charles / who was with youe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of Hune / Charles anſwered I wil not tell the / &amp; Iulian ſaith that vppon the thurſdaye folowing Charles taryed all daye in his houſe with greate fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / and appon fridaye folowyng yerlie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornyng before daye Charles went forth (as he ſaide) he went to paules and at his commyng in agayne he was in greate feare / ſaynge haſtelie geat me my horſſe / and with greate feare and haſt made him redie to ryde / &amp; bad maſtres portars lad leade his horſſe in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyld by the back ſyde / and than charles put in to his ſleue his maſe or maſor with other plate / and borowed of maſtres portar bothe gold &amp; ſyluer but howe much I am not ſure / and Charles went in to the feld after
<pb facs="tcp:10337:8"/> his horſſe &amp; I brought his boget after hym. Alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon fridaye in chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n as weke folowyng Charles cam whome late in the nyght / and brought with him iij. bakars and a ſmyth of ſtreat ford / and the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight they caried oute of Charles houſe all his goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es by the fylde ſyde to the bell at ſhordiche / and yer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y on the morowe conueyyd hit with cartes to ſtreat forde</p>
               <p>Moreouer Iulian ſaith that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaturdaye at night before the death of Hune Charles cam whome / and brought with hym a Gurnard ſayyng hit was for Hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne and charles boye telled to Iulian that there was alſo ordened for Hune a pece of freaſſh ſalmone wich Iohn bellynger had</p>
               <p>Alſo Charles ſaide to the ſaide Iulian / war not this an vngraciouſe trouble / I conde bryng my lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of London to the dores of heritiques in London booth of men and wemen that bene woorth M. lib. But I am ferd that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngraciouſe mydwyfe ſhallbe wraye vs all</p>
               <p>Alſo charles ſaide vnto maſtres porter in like wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe / and more larger ſayyng of the beſt in London / wherto maſtres porter anſwered / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt in London is my lord maire / than Charles ſaide / I wyll not ſkyll hym quite / for he taketh this matter whotte</p>
               <p>Where as Charles ioſeph ſaith he laye at neck hyll w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a harlot a mannes wife in baryngtons houſe the ſame night / &amp; there abode vntyll the morow at .xi. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock that Richard hune was morthered / wher vpon he bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught before the kynges councell for his purgacion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> forſaide baude baringtonnes wyſe / &amp; alſo thafforſaide Harlot / wich purgation we haue proued all vntrew as right larglie maye appere as well by the depoſicyon of Iulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> littell / as of thomas chitcheley taylor / &amp; of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſymons ſtacioner / with other / as of Robert iohnſon &amp; Peter torner</p>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <pb facs="tcp:10337:9"/>
               <head>¶The depoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Thomas chitcheley taylor</head>
               <p>The ſaide Thomas ſaith / the ſame monday y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> richard hune was founde deed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in a quarter of an houre after vij a clocke in the morning / he met w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Charles ioſeph co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng oute of Paules at the nether north dore / going toward pater noſt. rew / ſaing good morow M. Char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les / &amp; the ſaide charles anſwered / good morowe / &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned backe whan he was with oute the church doore / &amp; loked a pon the ſaide Chitcheley.</p>
               <p>The depoſicion of thomas ſymondes ſtacioner.</p>
               <p>He ſaith the ſame morning that Hune was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de deed / that within a quarter of an houre after vij. a clocke in the mornyng Charles Ioſeph cam before hym at his ſtalle / and ſaide good morowe goſſep Si<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons / and the ſame Symons ſaide good morowe to hym agayne / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiffe of the ſame Simons was by hym / and be cauſe of the deedly countenaunce &amp; haſtie goyng of Charles the ſaide Thomas bad his wiffe looke whither Charles gooyth / and as ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de perceyue Charles went in to an ale houſe ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng in Pater noſter rewe by the aley leydyng in to the roode of northdorne / or in to the aley / whither ſhe conde not well tell</p>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>¶The depoſicion of Robert iohnſon &amp; his wiffe dwellyng at the bell in ſhordiche / where Charles ioſeph ſet his horſſe that night y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he cam to towne to murther Richard Hune.</head>
               <p>The ſaide Robert ſaith that Charles ioſeph ſent his horſſe to his houſe a pon a holiedaye at night aboute .iij wekes before chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mas by a boye / which horſſe was albe ſweet / &amp; albe myred: &amp; the ſaide boy ſaide / laet my fathers horſſe ſtond ſadelled / for I cannot tell whether my father wyll ryde agayne to nyght or not / &amp; the ſayde horſſe ſtode ſaddelled all night / &amp; in the morning folow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Charles came booted &amp; ſporred aboute .viij. of the
<pb facs="tcp:10337:9"/> clocke / and axed if his horſſe was ſadelled / &amp; the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant anſwered yee / and the ſaide Charles leapt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his horſſe / &amp; prayed the hoſte to let hym oute at his backe gate / that he might ryde oute by the fyld ſyde / wich hoſte ſo did / and by cauſe he was vncertai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of the daye / we aſked him if he had herd ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Hune at &amp; tyme or not / &amp; he anſwered nay: but ſhortlye after he did. Neuertheles Peter torner Charles ſonne in lawe wich brought the horſſe by nyght in to the bell Robert iohnſons houſe / confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hit was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame night before that Hune was foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de deed in the mornyng</p>
               <p>Moreouer the frydaie before Hunes death Peter torner ſaide to an honeſt wooma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a waxchaundelers wife dwellyng before ſaint Maries ſpittel gate / that before this daye ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nyght Hune ſhuld haue a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuouſe deeth. And the ſame day at after none that Hune was founde deede the ſaide Peter cam to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me wife and tolde hir that Hune was hanged / ſayng what tolde I youe</p>
               <p>Alſo Iames the Chauncelers koke the friday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Hunes death ſaide to v. honeſt men that Hune ſhuld die or chriſtmas / or elles he wolde die for hym and on the monday that Hune was founde deede the ſaide Iames came to the ſame wemen / &amp; ſaide / what toolde I you / is he not now hanged.</p>
               <p>And we of thynqueſt axed both of Peter torner and of Iames kooke where they had knowlege that Hune ſhuld ſo ſhortlie die / and they ſaide in maſter Chauncelers place by euerie man</p>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>¶The depoſicion of Iohn ſpaldyng belrynger</head>
               <p>Fyrſt the ſaide deponent ſaith that on ſaturdaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond daye of December. Anno. 1514. he toke the charge of the preſone at .iiij. of the clocke at after noo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / by the commaundement of M. Chaunceler / &amp; ſo
<pb facs="tcp:10337:10"/> toke the keyys / wher vppon he gaue commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the ſaide deponent that he ſhuld let no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſone ſpeake with the preſoner / except he had knowlege of them / &amp; ſo at v. of the clocke the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me daye / the ſaide deponent went to the preſonner him ſealff a loone / &amp; ſe him and cheriſht him / where he gaue the ſaide deponent a pece of freaſhe ſalmone for his wiffe. And after that the ſaide depone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaith that he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to maſter Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menſaries to ſupper with his felowe / where he reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred that he had lefte his knyfe with the ſaide preſonner / where vppon by the councel of maſter Commenſarie he went to the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonner / and featched his kniffe / where he founde the preſonner / ſayng of his beades / &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide depone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t required his kniffe of the ſaide preſonner / &amp; the ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de preſonner deliuered the kniffe to the ſaide depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent gladlie / &amp; ſo departed for that night.</p>
               <p>And after that on the ſondaye next folowyng the ſaide depone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cam to the preſonner at ix. of the cloc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / &amp; axed him what meate he wold haue to his dyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner / &amp; he anſwered but a morſell / &amp; ſo the ſaide depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent departed &amp; weent to the Chaunceler in to the quere / and he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded that he ſhuld take the pene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenſarie vp to the preſonner with him to make him holie water &amp; holie bredde / and made the ſaide depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to departe the preſonne houſe for a while / &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he brought him his dynner &amp; locked Charles boye with him all dynner while / vnto the houre of i. of the clocke / &amp; ſo let the lad oute againe / &amp; axed him what he wolde haue to his ſoupper / &amp; he anſwered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had meate ynowghe &amp; ſo departed vntill vi. of the clock / &amp; then the ſaide deponent brought with him a quarte of Ale / &amp; at that time one William ſampton went with the ſaide deponent to ſe the preſonner / where he was and ſawe him and ſpake to geather / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10337:10"/> ſo from the houre of vi. aforſaide vnto xij.<note place="margin">there h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lyed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he ſhuld ſaye / b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a good ſcolema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter I warrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> youe / &amp; conning in ſuch buſines</note> a clocke on the morowe the ſaide deponent came not there / &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there he met y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chaunceler with other doctours going to ſee the preſonner / where he hanged</p>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>¶The depoſicion of Peter torner ſone in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of Charles Ioſeph</head>
               <p>Firſt he ſaithe that his father in lawe rode out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne on ſondaie the iij. day of December Anno xv C. and xiiij. at vi. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clocke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning / weering a coote of oreng tawncy / on a horſſe coloure griſol / trottyng</p>
               <p>He ſaith that on ſaturdaye next before that / one But<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tons wyte gaue knowlege to the ſaide deponent that his father ſhuld be areſted by dyuers ſeargeantes as ſone as he coude be taken / &amp; ther vppon the ſaide de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent gaue knowlege to his ſaide father in lawe / at the blacke friars at the water ſide / wher vppon he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded / &amp; the ſame night maſter Chaunceler gaue the keyys to Iohn belrynger / and gaue him charge of the preſonner / &amp; on the ſaide ſondaye the ſaide deponent with Iohn belrynger ſarued the ſaide preſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of his dynner at xij. of the clocke / &amp; then Iohn bellrynger ſaide to the depone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that he wold not cum to him vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the morowe / for my lorde had commaunded hym that the preſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner ſhuld haue but one meales meate of the daye. Not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng that / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide Iohn belryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had ſhutte Paules church dores weent to the forſaide preſonner with another with him / at vij. of the clocke at night the ſaide ſondaye</p>
               <p>And the ſaide deponent ſaith that he cam on the mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daie at the houre of viij. of the clocke in the mornyng to ſeeke Iohn bellrynger and conde not fynde him / <note place="margin">he was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſie otherwi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. chan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er &amp; ch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ph</note> &amp; taried vntill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hie maſſe of Paules was done / and yet he conde not fynd Iohn bellrynger / &amp; than Iohn bell<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryngers felowe / one Wylliam / deliuered the keyys to the ſaide
<pb facs="tcp:10337:11"/> deponent / &amp; ſo the ſaide deponent with ij. officers of my lordes being ſomners weent to ſerue the ſaide pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonner / and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cam they preſoner (they ſaide) was hanged his face to the wall warde / &amp; apon that the ſaide deponent Immediatelie gaue knowlege to the Chaunceler / wheruppon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chaunceler went vp with the maſter of the rolles / &amp; maſter ſubdeane / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other doctours vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to the nowmber of a doſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and theyre ſeruauntes</p>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>¶The depoſicion of Iohn enderbie barber</head>
               <p>The ſaide Iohn enderbie ſaith the fridaye before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deeth of Richard Hune betwyxt viij. &amp; ix. of the cloc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke in the mornyng he met with Iohn bellrynger in eſtcheape / &amp; axed of him how maſter Hune farede / the ſaide bellrynger anſwered ſayyng / there is ordened for him ſo greuouſe penawnce that whan men heare of hit / they ſhal haue greate meruayle ther of / witneſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes that herde Iohn bellrynger ſaye theſe woordes Iohn rutterſkriuenner and William ſegar armourer</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ie iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ellr ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>e to the aq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am not here tyl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ij of the clock of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aye</note>Alſo the ſaide Iohn enderbie ſaith / the ſame mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye that Richard Hune was founde deede / he met w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaide Iohn bellrynger at the coundythe in graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe ſtreate / aboute ix. of the clocke in the mornyng axeng the ſaide bellrynger howe maſter Hune fared / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide bellrynger anſwered ſaing / he fared well this daye in the mornyng betwixt v. and vi. of the klocke howbeit I am ſorie for him / for ther can no bodie co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to him vntill I come / for I haue the keyys of the dores heare by my gyrdell / and ſhewed keyys to the ſaide Enderbie</p>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>¶The depoſicion of Alen creſſwel wax chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deler</head>
               <p>The ſaide Alen ſaith that Iohn grandger ſeruaunt with my lord of London / in my lorde of Londons ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chin / at ſuche time as the ſaide Alen was ſeryng of Hunes coffe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that grandger tolde to him that he was preſent
<pb facs="tcp:10337:11"/> with Iohn bellrynger the ſame ſondaye at night that Richard Hune was found deed of the morowe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his keper ſet him in the ſtockes / in ſo mich the ſaide Hune deſired to borowe the kepers kniffe / &amp; the ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per axed him what he wolde doo with his kniffe / and Hune anſwered. I had leauer kyll my ſealffe than to be thus intreated / this depoſicion the ſaide Alen wil proue as farforth as any chriſten man maye / ſaing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grandger ſhewyd to him thiſe woordes of his awne frewyll and mynde / with oute any queſtion or enque<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to him made by the ſaide Alen / moreouer the ſaide Alen ſaith / that all that euenyng grandger was in greate feare</p>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>¶The depoſicion of Richard horſenaille baliue of the ſentuarie towne called good eſtur in eſſex</head>
               <p>The ſaide Richard ſaith the fridaye before Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenmas daye laſt paſt that one Charles Ioſeph ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner to my lorde of London be came a ſentuarie man / &amp; thaffore ſaide fridaye he regeſtred his name / the ſaide Charles ſayyng hit was fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaue garde of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die / for there bene ſertayne men in London ſo extreme againſt him for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deeth of Richard hune that he dar not abide in Londone / how be it the ſaide Charles ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ith he knowlegeth him ſealf gyltles of Hunes deeth for he deliuered the keyys to the Chaunceler by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes life / alſo the ſaide baliue ſaith / that Charles paide the dewtie of the ſaide regeſtring / bothe to him and to ſir Iohn ſtudeley vicar</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>¶The Copie of my lorde of Londons letter ſent to my lord Cardenall</head>
               <p>I Beſeche youre good lordſhip to ſtande ſo good lorde vnto my poore Chaunceler / now in warde / and endited by an vntrewe queſte for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deeth of Richard hune / vppon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onelie accuſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Charles Ioſeph made by paine &amp; duraunce that by youre interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10337:12"/> it may pleaſe the kynges grace to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie &amp; ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlie examined by indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſonnes of his diſcrete cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parties or there be any more done in the cauſe / &amp; that a pon the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie of my ſaide chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celer declared / it may further plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the kinges grace / to award a plackard vnto his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourney to confeſſe the ſaide endite ment to be vntre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we / when the tyme ſhall requere hit / for aſſured am I if my Chaunceler be tryed by any xij. men in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be ſo maliciouſlie ſet in fauore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereticae praui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatis / that is ar ſo ſet apon the fauoure of hereſie / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they will caſt and condemne my clarcke / thowght he war as innocent as Abel.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>keth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> al the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a citie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſealffe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utie</note> Quare ſi potes beate pater adiuua infirmitates noſtras et tibi in perpetuum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincti erimus / that is. Wherfore if you can / bleſſed fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther healp one infirmities and weaknes / &amp; we ſhalbe bounde to you for euer / Ouer this in moſte humble wife I beſeche youe that I may haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe fauoure / whome I neuer offended wyllinglie and that by youre good meanes I mought ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his grace / &amp; be fauorablie heerde / at any tyme it may ſo pleaſe his grace &amp; youe / and I with all myne ſhall praye for youre ꝓſperouſe eſtate lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinewe.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>your mooſt humble oratour R. L.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>¶The woordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my lorde of London ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the lordes in the parlement chaumber.</head>
               <p>Memorandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the buſſhop of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaide in the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t chaumber y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was a byll brought to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iurie that was charged vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deeth of Hune trewmen / &amp; ſaide &amp; toke a pon his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were falſſe periured caytiffes / &amp; ſaide further<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>more to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes there then beyng. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of god loke apon this matter / for if ye do not I dare not kepe myne awne houſe for heretiques / &amp; ſaide that the
<pb facs="tcp:10337:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaide Richard Hune hanged him ſealffe / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hit was his awne dede / &amp; no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes elles.<note place="margin">Hit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> woon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ther not bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wiffe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes to leat ſuch eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> kaepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it ys to be thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he ſaid not tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth in a moche as he <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>em no</note> And furthermore ſaide that there came a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his houſe (whoſe wiffe was apeched of hereſie) to ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym / &amp; he ſaide y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had no mynde to ſpeake w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpake &amp; reported to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame buſſhoppe that if his wife woold not holde ſtyll her opinion / he woold cutte her throte with his awne handes / with other woordes moare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sentence">
               <head>¶The ſentence of the queſt ſubſcribed by the Crowner.</head>
               <p>The inquiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intendend take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the citie of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the pariſhe of ſainte Gregorie in the warde of bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerd caſtell in London the vi. daye of Dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in the yere and raigne of Kyng Henry the viij. the vi. yere / afore Thomas Barnwell crowner of oure ſofferaine lord the Kyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the citie of London aforſaide. Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo afore Iames yarforde and Iohn mundie ſhriues of the ſaide citie / apon the ſight of the bodie of Rich<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ard hune late of London tayliour wich was founde hanged in lolars tower / and by the othe and proſe of lawfull men of the ſame warde / and of other iij. war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des next adioyning as hit ought to be after the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me in the citie aforſaide to enquere how and in what manner wiſe the ſaide Richard hune came vnto his deeth / &amp; apon the othe of Iohn barnarde / Thomas ſterre / William warren / Henry Abraham / Iohn abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe / Iohn turner / Robert alen / William marler / Iohn button / Iames page / Thomas pickhill / Wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liam burton / Robart brigewater / Thomas buſted / Gilbart howel / Richard Gybſon / Chriſtopher crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton / Iohn god / Richard holt / Iohn paſmere / Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond hudſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Iohn awncell / Richard couper / Iohn tynie / the wich ſaye vpon there othe that where the ſaide Richard hune by the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard
<pb facs="tcp:10337:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Buſſhop of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don was enpriſoned and brought to holde in a priſone of the ſaide Buſſhoppes called lolars tower lyyng in the cathedral church of S. Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le in London / in the pariſſhe of S. Gregorie in the warde of baynerd caſtell affore ſaide William horſey of London clarcke / otherwiſe called William herſie Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celer to Richard buſſhop of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; one Char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les ioſeph late of London<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſomner &amp; Iohn ſpalding of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe called Iohn belringer felonouſlie as felones to oure lord the Kyng with force and armes againſt the peace of oure ſofferaine Lord the Kyng / &amp; dignitie of his crowne / the .iiij. of daye December the yere of the raigne of oure ſofferaine Lord the .vi. affor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaide / of theire greate malice at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pariſhe of ſainte Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gorie afforſaide apon the ſaide Richard Hune made a fraye / &amp; the ſame Richard Hune felonouſlie ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelde &amp; ſmorderde / &amp; alſo the neck they did breake of the ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Richarde Hune &amp; there felonouſlie ſlewe hym and morthered hym / &amp; alſo the bodie of the ſaide Richard Hune afterward the ſame .iiij. daye / yere / place / pariſh &amp; warde afforſaide w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the proper gyrdell of the ſame Richard Hune of ſylcke / blacke of coloure / of the val<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue of .xij pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce after his deeth apon a hoke dryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to apece of tymber in the wal of the preſonne afforſaide made faſt / &amp; ſo ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged hym againſte the peace of oure ſofferaine Lorde the Kyng / &amp; the dignitie of his crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / and ſo the ſaide iurie hathe ſworne apon the holie Euangeliſte that they ſaide Wylliam Horſey clerck / Charles Ioſeph / &amp; Iohn Spaldyng of theyre ſet ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lice / then &amp; there felonouſlie kylled &amp; murthered the ſaide Richard Hune in Maner &amp; forme aboue ſaide againſt the peace of oure ſofferaine Lord the Kyng / his crowne &amp; dignitie. Subſcribed in this maner</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thomas Barnewell Crowner of the Citie of London.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:10337:13"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
